Guide to the Wesley E. Needham Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Wesley E. Needham Papers
1937-1988
1950-1988
Tibet MSS 64
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
20.6
(50 boxes)
Correspondence with Tibetan language scholars, Tibetan religious and government officials, and others, 1937-1988; and related materials, 1950s-1980s, including research materials, notes, writings, and translations by Needham; subject files about Diluv Khutagt, Anzhai Li, Edna Bryner, and Tibetan materials in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library; clippings, other printed materials; photographs; and artifacts relating to Tibet, Tibetan literature and art, and Needham's curatorship of the Beinecke Library's Tibetan collection. Correspondents include Bstan-'dzin-rgya-mtsho, Dalai Lama XIV, and his representatives; Tsipon Shuguba and members of his family; and Chögyam Trungpa.
Needham, Wesley E., 1903-1992
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Wesley E. Needham, 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Associated material: Edna Bryner Papers (Tibet Mss 65) Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Wesley E. Needham (1903-1992)
Wesley E. Needham (Yale 1954 MA honorary), scholar of Tibetan art, language, and literature, and Adviser in Tibetan Literature, Yale University Library, 1953-1992. Needham also worked for Bullard's furniture store in New Haven, and he was an architectural draftsman for James Gamble Rogers, New York City, 1929-1930s, participating in the construction of Yale University buildings including Trumbull College, Sterling Memorial Library, the Hall of Graduate Studies, and the Law School.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence with Tibetan language scholars, Tibetan religious and government officials, and others, 1937-1988; and related materials, 1950s-1980s, including research materials, notes, writings, and translations by Needham; subject files about Diluv Khutagt, Anzhai Li, Edna Bryner, and Tibetan materials in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library; clippings, other printed materials; photographs; and artifacts relating to Tibet, Tibetan literature and art, and Needham's curatorship of the Beinecke Library's Tibetan collection. Correspondents include Bstan-'dzin-rgya-mtsho, Dalai Lama XIV, and his representatives; Tsipon Shuguba and members of his family; and Chögyam Trungpa.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1937-1988. II. Other Papers, circa 1950s-1988. III. Textiles and Objects, circa 1950s-1988.
Art, Tibetan; Buddhism -- China -- Tibet Autonomous Region; Tankas (Tibetan scrolls); Tibetan literature; Tibetan language -- Study and teaching; Tibet Autonomous Region (China); Photographs -- Tibet -- 20th Century; Flags -- Tibet -- 20th Century; Bryner, Edna, 1886-1967; Bstan-ʼdzin-rgya-mtsho, Dalai Lama XIV, 1935-; B. Zhamsranzhav, Dilav Khutagt, 1884-1965; Li, Anzhai; Needham, Wesley E., 1903-1992; Trungpa, Chögyam, 1939-1987; Tsipon Shuguba, 1904-1991; Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library; Yale University. Library
- Correspondence, 1937-1988; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent name, followed by a chronological file of outgoing carbons, 1967-1984, and unsorted correspondence.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Additional correspondence is filed by subject in Series II. Other Papers.
  Scope and Contents
  Some files contain related materials, including records of Beinecke Library acquisitions, writings by Needham or others, clippings, or printed ephemera.
  - Adams, F. B., Jr., 1959 January 21 (Box 1)
  - Ahmad, Zahiruddin, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Allcroft, Charles, undated (Box 1)
  - Alterman, Benjamin, 1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Arnoldi, Giuseppe, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Associated Press, 1957 August 26 (Box 1)
  - Atmore, Robert C., 1958 November (Box 1)
  - Barry, Robert J., 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Bazl, Frank M., 1962-1978, undated (Box 1)
  - Bechert, Heinz, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Berk, Maurice, 1961 November 29 (Box 1)
  - Bett, W. D. L., 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Bills, Sheila Coffin, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Bischoff, Friedrich, 1968 March 21 (Box 1)
  - Bose, Vivian, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Bowles, Chester, 1955-1959 (Box 1)
  - Brooks, Ernest, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Browar, Lisa, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Andrew H. (Andrew Hutton), 1957 May 2 (Box 1)
  - Brown, W. Norman (William Norman), 1962 November 27 (Box 1)
  - Bruckner, Geraldine, 1959 January 27 (Box 1)
  - Bstan-'dzin-rgya-mtsho, Dalai Lama XIV, 1944-1980, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Buford, Sidney A., 1951 December 28 (Box 1)
  - Cassidy, William L., 1971 June (Box 1)
  - Chadwick, Hal, 1958 March (Box 1)
  - Chang, Kun, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Chʻen, Kenneth K. S. (Kenneth Kuan Shêng), 1955 August 19 (Box 1)
  - Chhodak, Tenzing, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Christian Science Monitor, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Clapp, Verner W. (Verner Warren), 1951-1953 (Box 1)
  - Clark, Dorothy, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Coffey, Katherine, 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - Cole, Grover, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Colton, Philip, Jr., 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Colton, Wendall P., Jr., 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Cooper, Martha, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Cossley Batt, Jill (Box 1)
  - Cranbrook Institute of Science, 1964-1971, undated (Box 2)
  - Culmback, Barrett W., 1970 (Box 2)
  - Cutting, C. Suydam (Charles Suydam), 1946-1949 (Box 2)
  - Dart, Robert Paul, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - de Kay, Drake, 1957-1959 (Box 2)
  - Dentan, Robert C. (Robert Claude), 1951 September 21 (Box 2)
  - Desfor, Max, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Dhardo, Rimpoche, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Dharma Publishing, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Dhondup, K., 1978 November 16 (Box 2)
  - Dimitrieff, N. V., 1958 July 30 (Box 2)
  - Donath, Dorothy C., 1969 October (Box 2)
  - Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1951-1957 (Box 2)
  - Draghi, Paul Alexander, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Dresden, M. J., 1963 March (Box 2)
  - E. P. Dutton, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Edgerton, Franklin, and Eleanor Edgerton, 1944-1967 (Box 2)
  - Emerson, Faye, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Engelsmann, William H., 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Engley, Donald B. (Donald Brown), 1960 (Box 2)
  - Evangelical and Reformed Church. Theological Seminary, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Evans, Roger F., 1955 (Box 2)
  - Evens-Wentz, W. Y., 1960-1964 (Box 2)
  - Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton), 1957 (Box 2)
  - Far East Foundation, 1952 July (Box 2)
  - Farmer, M. K., undated (Box 2)
  - Field Museum of Natural History, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Ford, John, 1982 September 17 (Box 2)
  - Friedrich, Walter G., 1959 March 9 (Box 2)
  - Frye, Stanley, 1972-1975, undated (Box 2)
  - Fuller, John G., 1979 (Box 2)
  - Fussler, Herman Howe, 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Gallup, Donald Clifford, 1957 September 30 (Box 2)
  - Gamble, Charles K., 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - George, Christopher S., 1966-1974 (Box 2)
  - Glazier, William S., 1959 April 23 (Box 2)
  - Glusker, Erwin, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Gombo, Ugen, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Gomez, Luis, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
  - Gordon, Antoinette K., 1975-1976, undated (Box 3)
  - Gordon, David, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Grabel, Richard, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Graham, Elliott, 1954 March 23 (Box 3)
  - Grasson, Albert J., 1955 February 21 (Box 3)
  - Griffin, Herbert M., 1955 January 31 (Box 3)
  - Grunfeld, A. Tom, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Grupper, Samuel Martin, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Gyalpo, Tamdin D., 1968-1972 (Box 3)
  - Haber, Martha C., 1954 November (Box 3)
  - Hardage, Sylvia Deak, 1970, undated (Box 3)
  - Harmony Buddhist Mission, 1959, undated (Box 3)
  - Harper's Magazine, 1957 August 7 (Box 3)
  - Harrison, Joseph G., 1957 August 7 (Box 3)
  - Hart, Kay, 1957 May 13 (Box 3)
  - Hartman, Charles, 1963-1967 (Box 3)
  - Hatt, Robert T. (Robert Torrens), 1969 March 10 (Box 3)
  - Haverbeck, H. D. S. (Harrison Donald Seaman), 1958 November 11 (Box 3)
  - Heeramaneek, Nasli, Mr. and Mrs., 1959 June 10 (Box 3)
  - Henkle, Herman Henry, 1959 May 5 (Box 3)
  - Herald Tribune, 1957 March (Box 3)
  - Hoffmann, Helmut, 1974-1979, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Holden, Reuben A. (Reuben Andrus), 1957 October 14 (Box 3)
  - Horch, Louis L., 1955-1957 (Box 3)
  - Horne, David, 1961 January 5 (Box 3)
  - Houston, Gary, 1973, undated (Box 3)
  - Hummel, Siegbert, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Huntington, Ellsworth, Mrs., undated (Box 3)
  - Hurd, Charles P., 1957 July 19 (Box 3)
  - Hutchinson, Allan C., 1955 July 21 (Box 3)
  - Hutchinson, Terrell W., 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - India. Government, 1967 (Box 3)
  - The Institute for Advanced Studies of World Religions, 1972, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Jacques Marchais Center of Tibetan Art, 1980 September 4 (Box 3)
  - Jamlo, Paltul, 1970, undated (Box 3)
  - Jigme Singye Wangchuck, 1958 October 14 (Box 3)
  - Joyaux, Alain, 1978 May (Box 3)
  - Kamer, Henri A., 1972 April (Box 3)
  - Kanakura, Enshō, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Kataoka, H., 1985 July 28 (Box 3)
  - Kellems, Vivien, 1954-1957 (Box 3)
  - Kerr, Robert Riggs, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Kerstein, Barbara Prue, 1958 September 30 (Box 3)
  - Kezerian, Stephen A., 1961-1964 (Box 3)
  - Khendup, L., 1970 (Box 4)
  - Kittoe, N. D., 1958 (Box 4)
  - Koven, Leo J., 1971 (Box 4)
  - Kuløy, Hallvard Kȧre, 1977 July (Box 4)
  - Kusek, Sally, 1977 (Box 4)
  - La Gorce, John Oliver, 1957 April 9 (Box 4)
  - Lall, Sohan, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Lamm, Mari, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Lansing, Gerrit Y., 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Lattimore, Owen, 1967 November 7 (Box 4)
  - Lavitt, Edwin M., 1960 October 12 (Box 4)
  - Lhalungpa, Lobsang Phuntshok, 1977; 2 (Box 4)
  - Lhalungpa, Lobsang Phuntshok, and Valentine, Allen, 1952-1974 (Box 4)
  - Li, Juan, undated (Box 4)
  - Lingham, Carol, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Lobsang Phuntsok, 1950-1955 (Box 4)
  - Lokesh Chandra, 2 (Box 4)
  - Lucie Bolduc, Inc., 1980 (Box 4)
  - Luzac & Co., 1962 May 29 (Box 4)
  - McBride, Lucy, 1960 December 15 (Box 4)
  - McCormick Theological Seminary, 1959-1966 (Box 4)
  - McCullough, Andrew, 1982 March (Box 4)
  - Macrae, Elliott B., 1958-1968 (Box 4)
  - McLaughlin, Barkley Roy, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Maddacks, Ray T., 1952-1962 (Box 4)
  - Malalasekera, G. P. (Gunapala Piyasena), 1962 January 31 (Box 4)
  - Marboro Books, 1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1955 December 16 (Box 4)
  - Maurer, Walter Harding, 1957-1959 (Box 4)
  - Mayall, Robert, 1962 November (Box 4)
  - Meisezahl, R. O. (Richard O.), 1968, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Meiss, Edwin R., Mrs., 1961 June 26 (Box 4)
  - Melby, John F. (John Fremont)., 1955 November 17 (Box 4)
  - Mettenleiter, M. W., 1962 January (Box 4)
  - Miller, Robert J., Mr. and Mrs., 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - Mitsushima, Tadasu, 1975 January (Box 4)
  - Moore, Sandra, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Morris, Ira V., 1958-1959 (Box 5)
  - Morris, Raymond P., 1967 (Box 5)
  - Mukhopadhyay, K. L., 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Museum of International Folk Art (N.M.), 1960 October 28 (Box 5)
  - Namgyal Institute of Tibetology, 1964 May 15 (Box 5)
  - Napier, Nelda N., 1952 (Box 5)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1979-1980; 2 (Box 5)
  - National Geographic Magazine, 1959 October 16 (Box 5)
  - New World Foundation, 1957 October 28 (Box 5)
  - Newark Museum, 1959-1979 (Box 5)
  - Nordbeck, Theodore M., 1952-1953 (Box 5)
  - Office of Tibet (New York, N.Y.), 1967-1973 (Box 5)
  - O'Leary, M. Bede, 1954 (Box 5)
  - Parker, William R., 1957 February 8 (Box 5)
  - Peterson, Stephen L., 1975 July (Box 5)
  - Pierson, George Wilson, 1979 April (Box 5)
  - Poleman, H. I. (Horace Irvin), 1962 November 27 (Box 5)
  - Poppe, Nicholas, 1967 December (Box 5)
  - Porter, Lucius Chapin, 1954 June (Box 5)
  - Powell, Harry H., Jr., 1971 December (Box 5)
  - Rashi Gempil Ling First Kalmuk Buddhist Temple, 1980 September (Box 5)
  - Rato, Khyongla, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Rees, Richard A., 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Reid, Samuel, 1952 September 29 (Box 5)
  - Rice, Donald, 1954 July 19 (Box 5)
  - Ripley, S. Dillon (Sidney Dillon), 1960-1979 (Box 5)
  - Roach, Michael, 1979-1980; 3 (Box 5)
  - Robbins, Michelle, 1981 November (Box 6)
  - Robinson, John J., 1968 (Box 6)
  - Rogers, William G., 1959 (Box 6)
  - Rosenthal, Bernard M., 1969 January (Box 6)
  - Rostow, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Rowe, David Nelson, 1959 October 30 (Box 6)
  - Ruegg, David Seyfort, 1962 (Box 6)
  - St. Denis, Gilbert, 1969 February (Box 6)
  - San Francisco Public Library, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Sargent, Lena K., 1954 June (Box 6)
  - Sasaki, Genjun H., 1960 November 21 (Box 6)
  - Sekai Bunka Publishing, Inc., 1974 December (Box 6)
  - Semo, Gabriel A., 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Shafer, Robert, 1954 December 1 (Box 6)
  - Shakabpa, Norzin, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Shanck, Louis M., 1954 July 19 (Box 6)
  - Shell, Selenea, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Short, Kay, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Shulman, Edythe K., 1960 (Box 6)
  - Sikkim Research Institute of Tibetology, undated (Box 6)
  - Sinha, Nirmal Chandra, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Sinor, Denis, 1964 September 4 (Box 6)
  - Slaggert, Alfred N., 1954-1957 (Box 6)
  - Smith, E. Gene (Ellis Gene), 1957-1969; 2 (Box 6)
  - Snellgrove, David L., 1958-1966 (Box 6)
  - Spear, Nathaniel, Jr., 1964-1967 (Box 6)
  - Springer, Lois, 1970 November (Box 6)
  - Staudlinger, Else, 1955 August 16 (Box 6)
  - Steinberger, C. H., 1958 September 4 (Box 6)
  - Street, John C., 1958 March 4 (Box 6)
  - Sturges, Janet Gallaudet, 1967-1969 (Box 6)
  - Talbot, Linda, 1967-1968, undated (Box 6)
  - Taring, J., 1966 May (Box 6)
  - Teramoto, Enga, 1937 (Box 6)
  - Tesniere, Bernard A., 1968 (Box 6)
  - Thubten Jigme Norbu, 1966-1970; 2 (Box 6)
  - The Tibet Journal, 1973-1978 (Box 7)
  - Tibetan Collection, Beinecke Library. The Kanjur, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Tibetan Collection, Beinecke Library. Tibetan Literature, 1964 January 5 (Box 7)
  - Tibetan Collection, Beinecke Library. Repairs, 1967 December 2 (Box 7)
  - Tibetan Collection, Beinecke Library. Tanka Paintings, undated (Box 7)
  - The Tibetan Spaniel Club of America, Inc., 1975 April (Box 7)
  - Trenholme, Russell, 1965-1979; 2 (Box 7)
  - Tresidder, Argus John, 1957 January 28 (Box 7)
  - Trinity College (Hartford, Conn.). Library, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
  - Trungpa, Chögyam, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Tsipon Shuguba, and Shuguba family, 1940s-1960s; 6 (Box 7)
  - University of Kentucky. Libraries, 1976-1977 (Box 7)
  - Valparaiso University, 1959 March 4 (Box 7)
  - Van Hoogstraten, Jan S. F., 1955 July 25 (Box 7)
  - Van Zanten, David, 1980 June (Box 7)
  - Verosky, Joan, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Verrill, Agnes, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Vreeland, Herbert Harold, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Wald, George, 1969 (Box 8)
  - Walker, Richard L., 1953 September 21 (Box 8)
  - Wan, Weiying, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Weiler, Joseph, 1974, 1984 (Box 8)
  - Wiener, Doris, 1972-1974 (Box 8)
  - Williams, Hugh E. (Disciples for Christ Historical Society), 1972 October (Box 8)
  - Windsor, David L., 1957 July 19 (Box 8)
  - Wood, Raymond L., 1963 May (Box 8)
  - World Order and Asia Publishing House, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
  - Wright, Arthur F., 1954-1958 (Box 8)
  - Yankee, 1954-1955 (Box 8)
  - Zumbro, William M., 1963 (Box 8)
  - Chronological file, 1967-1984; 2 (Box 8)
    Outgoing carbons
  - Unsorted, 1947-1988 (Box 8)
- Other Papers, circa 1950s-1980s; 17.05; (39 boxes)
  Roughly organized by subject, with some overlapping content. Folders are unarranged.
  Some files contain correspondence.
  - Biographical information, 6 (Box 9)
  - Early Tibetan studies, 2 (Box 9)
  - Early Tibetan studies, 5 (Box 10)
  - Early Tibetan studies (Box 11)
  - Research notes, 11 (Box 11)
  - Yale publications and information, 5 (Box 12)
  - Beinecke collection. Publicity, 5 (Box 12)
  - Research notes. Encyclopedia articles by Needham (Box 12)
  - Research notes. Encyclopedia articles by Needham, 3 (Box 13)
  - Beinecke collection. Dorje and bell, 5 (Box 13)
  - Research notes and copies of texts, 4 (Box 14)
  - Research notes. Tibetan art, 4 (Box 14)
  - Research notes. Tibetan art (Box 15)
  - Offprints, 4 (Box 15)
  - Offprints, 8 (Box 16)
  - Periodicals, world Buddhism, 4 (Box 17)
  - Buddhism in the West, 4 (Box 17)
  - Tibetan students, 2 (Box 17)
  - Tibetan students, 6 (Box 17)
  - The Institute for Advanced Studies of World Religions, 8 (Box 18)
  - Tibetan Review, 6 (Box 19)
  - Research notes. Hayagriva, 5 (Box 19)
  - Research notes. Hayagriva, 4 (Box 20)
  - Research materials, 6 (Box 20)
  - Tibetan art photographs and plates, 5 (Box 21)
  - Tibetan collection, 4 (Box 21)
  - Tibetan collection (Box 49)
  - Tibetan art notes, 6 (Box 22)
  - Periodicals on Tibet, 3 (Box 22)
  - Periodicals on Tibet, 9 (Box 23)
  - Periodicals on Tibet, 6 (Box 24)
  - Periodicals on Tibet, 4 (Box 25)
  - Newspaper articles on Tibet, 3 (Box 25)
  - Newspaper articles on Tibet, 8 (Box 26)
  - Newspaper articles on Tibet, 6 (Box 27)
  - Maharaja of Sikkim, 3 (Box 27)
  - Maharaja of Sikkim, 2 (Box 28)
  - Diluv Khutagt, 7 (Box 28)
  - Diluv Khutagt, 4 (Box 29)
  - Li, Anzhai. Manuscripts and correspondence, 7 (Box 29)
  - Li, Anzhai. Manuscripts and correspondence, 9 (Box 30)
  - Golden Lotus Press, 8 (Box 31)
  - Beinecke collection cataloging and research, 3 (Box 31)
  - Beinecke collection cataloging and research, 6 (Box 32)
  - Beinecke Kanjur, 3 (Box 32)
  - Beinecke Kanjur, 5 (Box 33)
  - Exhibitions of Tibetan books, 4 (Box 33)
  - Bryner, Edna. Gifts to the Beinecke Library, 3 (Box 33)
  - Materials about the Tibetan collection, 14 (Box 34)
  - Materials about the Tibetan collection, 10 (Box 35)
  - Materials about the Tibetan collection, 16 (Box 36)
  - Materials about the Tibetan collection, 10 (Box 37)
  - "Kanjur MSS sheets", 5 (Box 38)
  - Tibetan books in other collections, 2 (Box 39)
  - Beinecke Tibetan collection bookplates (Box 39)
  - Unsorted, 9 (Box 39)
  - Card file. "Bernard Collection: Tibetan Manuscripts: 28-116" (Box 40)
  - Card file. Unidentified (Box 41)
  - Card file. Unidentified (Box 42)
  - Card file. Unidentified (Box 43)
  - Card file. Unidentified (Box 44)
  - Card file. Unidentified (Box 45)
  - Card file. Unidentified (Box 46)
  - Card file. Unidentified (Box 47)
- Textiles and Objects, circa 1950s-1980s; 0.42; (3 boxes)
  - Book covers (Box 48)
  - Textiles for tanka frames (Box 48)
  - Textiles for tanka frames (Box 49)
  - Tibetan flag (Box 50)
    Accompanied by related correspondence
  - Tibetan paper (Box 49)